William S. Griffith Papers
William S. Griffith Papers
1955-2008
Griffith, William S., 1932-1996.
12 linear ft.
Papers of the adult education professor and researcher. Includes Griffith's correspondence and his own writings (articles, book chapters, reports, speeches) as well as an extensive amount of relevant material by others including articles and clippings, conference proceedings, papers, reports and studies, speeches, and printed material. The collection reflects Griffith's interest in international education (material from countries ranging from Africa and Asia to Scotland and Sweden), correctional education (particularly for sex offenders), and population education (Planned Parenthood, population education in Egypt). There is also a considerable amount of material from organizations with which Griffith was closely involved, including the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE), the Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), the Northwest Adult Education Association, and the Universities of Chicago and of British Columbia.
2469509
Biographical History
William S. Griffith earned his Ph.D. in Adult Education in 1963 from the University of Chicago. He was a professor of Adult Education at the University of British Columbia and the University of Chicago, and taught at Virginia Polytechnic Institute, Australian National University and the University of Sydney. He was an active member of the Commission of Adult Education, President of the Northwest Adult Education Association (1990-1991), Chairman of the Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), and President of the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE). He also served on the steering committee of the Adult Education Research Conference (AERC) and chaired the program committees for the AEA/USA and the NAPCAE national conferences (in 1966 and 1975 respectively) and the Research Section of the National University Extension Association. In 1986-1987, Griffith spent a year in the Philippines as part of a joint pilot project of SEAMEO and the Canadian International Development Agency (CIDA).
Bill Griffith had a number of research interests including extension education, correctional education, literacy, population education and international education. He wrote extensively on these and other topics -- articles, books, papers, speeches, reports, and studies -- and made a significant contribution to the field by co-editing (with Howard McClusky) the 8-volume Adult Education Association Handbook Series in Adult Education in 1980-1981.
His contributions to the field have been widely recognized. He was named a Fulbright-Hayes Senior Research Fellow to Australia in 1972-1973, and in 1980 the AEA/USA awarded him its Research to Practice award as well as its Leadership Award.
Bill Griffith died on August 12, 1996 at the age of 64.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William S. Griffith Papers represent the papers and research material of the adult educator and researcher. They reflect Griffith's research interests in population education, correctional education, extension education, and international comparative education. There is also a considerable amount of material from organizations with which Griffith was closely involved, including the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE), the Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), the Northwest Adult Education Association, and the Universities of Chicago and of British Columbia.
The first three series comprise Griffith's own output. Biographical material is sparse, consisting of two interviews, a clipping from the University of British Columbia alumni magazine, and some campaign fliers from Griffith's campaign for AAACE President. Correspondence-subject files consists of correspondence with individuals (Robert Luke, Roger Clark), organizations (among them AAACE, CPAE, the Fielding Institute, and Planned Parenthood Federation of Canada), and universities (University of Chicago, Pennsylvania State University, Universiti Pertanian Malaysia, University of Calgary), as well as clusters of topical information (adult basic education, correctional education, literacy, population education) and specific activities or projects with which Griffith was involved, including the International Symposium on Adult Education, Rape and Violence End Now (RAVEN), the Ukrainian Dairy Training School, and the South East Asian Ministers of Education Organization (SEAMEO). The latter has material from Griffith's year in the Philippines under the auspices of SEAMEO/CIDA, including background material on education in the Philippines, a course description, and Griffith's own notes from regular meetings held during that year in the Philippines. Writings comprises Griffith's articles, books, class syllabi and curricula, manuscripts, papers, reports, reviews, and speeches. Of particular interest are the 30+ manuscript papers on various aspects of community colleges. It is unclear whether these were intended eventually to be merged into a book or whether they were written for different times and occasions and simply share a theme.
The remaining series organize material collected by Griffith as relevant to his interests, but not written by him. Articles (by others) contains reprints, photocopies and clippings of articles on topics related to adult education; the earliest item is a photocopy of the text of a speech delivered at the University of Michigan in 1855; the latest are transparencies of two Calvin and Hobbes comic strips.
Griffith attended (and presented at) a vast number of Conferences; this series includes material from nearly 50 conferences covering more than thirty years, and provides an overview of the changing emphases in adult education during that time. The material is in order by conference name. If the sponsoring organization is not part of the name, and if there is a single sponsoring organization, its name is given in parenthesis following the conference title.
Griffith also amassed a valuable library of papers, reports, studies, speeches and printed material on adult education-related topics. Papers (by others) comprises scholarly papers written by others in the field, including a substantial 1940s paper by well-known adult educator Cyril O. Houle on "Adult Education as a Function of State Government." Reports and studies (by others) represents a comprehensive 40-year overview of the field of adult education worldwide in the form of formal reports and studies undertaken by organizations, foundations and government agencies in the United States, Canada, and around the world. The documents are divided into particular topics (Adult Basic Education (ABE), correctional education, extension education, literacy, and women's education) and Miscellaneous; the Miscellaneous papers are then subdivided by geographic area and range from Scotland to Iran to Africa. Speeches (by others) contains the text of miscellaneous speeches. Theses (by others) contains more than 25 masters theses and doctoral dissertations, for which Dr. Griffith was the faculty adviser or a dissertation committee member.Printed material is a motley collection of brochures, pamphlets, handouts, booklets and fliers from a variety of organizations, associations, and agencies.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically, with the exception of the subdivisions "Books" and "Classes and curricula" under Writings; these are arranged chronologically.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, the researcher may wish to consult the following:
American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE)
Commission for Professors of Adult and Continuing Education (CPAE)
Separated Material
Some items have been removed from the collection for separate cataloging. For more information on these items, please contact the repository listed above or search with "William S. Griffith" as "Keyword Anywhere."
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Griffith, William S., 1932-1996.; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.; Commission for Professors of Adult Education.; National Association for Public Continuing & Adult Education.; Adult education.; Adult education educators.; Adult education -- Evaluation.; Adult education -- Research.; Adult education teachers -- Training of.; Agricultural extension work -- Research.; Birth control.; Community colleges.; Continuing education.; Prisoners -- Education.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Dissertations.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Papers (document genres); Periodicals.; Proceedings.; Proposals.; Reports.; Theses.; Studies.; Adult educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority of papers, gift of William S. Griffith. Theses and dissertations, gift of Beverly Griffith, 2008.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Clippings about, 1980; 1989; AAACE president campaign flyer; interview in University of British Columbia alumni magazine (Box 1)
  - Interview transcript, 1987 (Box 1)
    See also South East Asian Ministers of Organization (SEAMEO)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Adult Basic Education (ABE), 1986-1989; undated (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Reports: Cooperative Program Improvement: An Experiment in ABE In-Service Training; Conferences: Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE)
  - Adult Education Research Centre curriculum review, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Alberta Association for Continuing Education, 1991 (Box 1)
  - American Association of Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE)
    - Adult Learning editorial board, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Audit (Lloyd Richardson), undated (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, undated (Box 1)
    - Campaign fliers, undated (Box 1)
    - Conferences, See Conferences: American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1993; undated; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Financial statements, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Leadership roster, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Meetings
      - Board of Directors, 1987; 1991-1992; 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Executive Committee, 1989-1992; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Plan of consolidation, AEA/ NAPCAE, 1982; plan to merge AEA/USA with NAPCAE to create the AAACE (Box 1)
    - Policies and procedures, 1988; 1989 (Box 1)
    - Printed material
      - Discussion papers, 1978; 1979 (Box 1)
      - Newsletters, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
      - Speaker's Bureau booklet, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Strategic plan, 1991 (Box 1)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges, 1969; newsletters and several papers/reports (Box 1)
  - California, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    See also Reports and studies: Miscellaneous: California
  - Canadian Association for the Study of Adult Education (CASAE), 1986; 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    See also Conferences: Canadian Association for the Study of Adult Education (CASAE) 13th Annual
  - Caritas Adult and Higher Education Service (Hong Kong), 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - The Cedar Glen Declaration
    See Literacy
  - Centre for Community and Global Transformation Learning, 1993; course description, Budd Hall (Box 1)
  - Clark, Roger, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Commission On Adult Basic Education (COABE), See Adult Basic Education (ABE)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), 1978; 1986,; 1993-1994,; undated (Box 1)
    See also Conferences: Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE)
  - Correctional education, 1980-1985; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    See also Reports and studies: Correctional education
  - Council of Europe (Conseil de l'Europe), 1975; 1977,; 1978,; 1981-1982,; 1986; correspondence, several papers and reports (Box 1)
  - Ethics, 1986; 1991,; undated (Box 1)
    See also "Michigan"
  - Fielding Institute, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Florida State University, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Graduate programs in extension education in Canada (list), undated (Box 1)
  - Hall, Budd, See Centre for Community and Global Transformation Learning
  - Illinois, 1964; 1969,; 1970,; 1979,; undated; printed matter, report, history of the Adult Education Round Table of Northern Illinois (Box 1)
    See also University of Chicago; Reports and studies: Illinois
  - Institute for the Study of Adult Literacy, 1987 (Box 1)
  - International Adult Education Hall of Fame, 2006; 2008; newsletter, program, call for papers (Box 1)
  - International Conference on Foreign Student Affairs, 1971; evaluation form (Box 1)
  - International Symposium on Adult Education (Shenyang, China), 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Literacy, 1976; 1987,; 1989 (Box 1)
    See also Reports and studies: Literacy
  - Loughborough University of Technology Centre for Extension Studies, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Luke, Robert, 1991; includes draft of a chapter from Luke's The NEA and Adult Education 1921-1971 (Box 2)
  - "Michigan" [supplied title], undated; handouts concerning development of a code of ethics for adult educators (Box 2)
  - Ministry of Education, Canada, 1981-1982; includes report, "Continuing Education: The Third System" (Box 2)
  - National Adult and Continuing Education Week, 1988 (Box 2)
  - National Association for Public and Continuing Adult Education (NAPCAE), 1978 (Box 2)
    See also AAACE: Plan of consolidation, AAACE/ NAPCAE
  - Nigeria, 1975; 1993-1994,; undated; correspondence with the Federal Ministry of Education, University of Ibadan, and individuals; UNESCO report; working paper on adult education trends in Africa (Box 2)
  - Northwest Adult Education Association
    - Board members, 1983-1989 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Meeting minutes, 1983-1988 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters, 1986-1995; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Policies and procedures, 1985; 1987,; 1988 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Pennsylvania State University, See Writings: Classes and Curricula: Evaluation in Adult and Extension Education
  - Philippines, See South East Asian Ministers of Education Organization (SEAMEO)
  - Philosophy of adult education inventory, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood Association of British Columbia, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of Canada, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - Population education - Egypt, 1977 (Box 2)
  - RAVEN (Rape And Violence End Now), 1983; undated (Box 2)
  - Society of Population Educators, 1979; newsletter with meeting minutes (Box 2)
  - South East Asian Ministers of Education Organization (SEAMEO), 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Southern Alberta Institute of Technology, undated (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian Dairy Training School, 1992 (Box 2)
  - United States Department of Education, 1982; 1988,; 1989,; 1990,; 1993 (Box 2)
  - Universiti Pertanian Malaysia, 1995 (Box 2)
  - University of British Columbia, 1978; 1987,; 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    See also Adult Education Research Centre curriculum review
  - University of Calgary, 1993; graduate program proposal (Box 2)
  - University of Chicago, 1957; 1960; 1967; 1968; proposal for an adult education center, two reports; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - University of Chicago Adult Education alumni, 1983; 1996,; 1997; letters, photos, etc. to Griffith from alumni of the program (Box 2)
  - University College of Swansea, 1995; correspondence, draft of two papers (one by Griffith) (Box 2)
  - University of New England (New South Wales), 1986 (Box 2)
  - University of Oklahoma, 1993 (Box 2)
  - University of Saskatchewan, 1993 (Box 2)
  - University of Sydney Centre for Continuing Education, 1984 (Box 2)
  - University of Wisconsin, ca. 1989 (Box 2)
  - Vancouver School of Theology, 1994 (Box 2)
  - Worker's Educational Association of New South Wales, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
- Writings
  See also Correspondence subject files: University College of Swansea
  - Articles
    - "Adult Education" (for the Academic American Encyclopedia), 1995; correspondence and drafts (Box 2)
    - Literacy Discussion, vol. 4 no. 3, 1973; thematic issue on "Adult Basic Education II" edited by Griffith (Box 2)
    - "The McGrath Report: A Critique", 1969; in Journal of Cooperative Extension, vol. 7 no. 2 (Box 2)
    - "NCA Standards for Adult High Schools", 1975; in North Central Association Quarterly, vol. 49 no. 4 (Box 2)
    - "North America: Adult Education" (for the International Encyclopedia of Adult and Continuing Education), 1991 (Box 2)
    - "Paolo Freire: Utopian Perspective on Literacy Education for Revolution", 1974; in Literacy Discussion (Box 2)
    - "Perspectives on Continuing Education", 1976; in Connecticut Medicine, vol. 40 no. 11 (Box 2)
    - "Report from the Consultant", 1975; in Proceedings of the Veterinary Self-Assessment Workshop (Box 2)
    - "The Role of Public School Adult Education", 1965; in The High School Journal, vol. 49 no. 2 (Box 2)
  - Books
    - "Learning Theory" (chapter 2 of Extension Handbook, 1st ed, edited by Donald J. Blackburn), 1984 (Box 3)
    - "Adult Education Leaders Should Come From Within Adult Education" (chapter in Confronting Controversies in Challenging Times), 1992 (Box 3)
    - "Applying Learning Theory in Extension Work" and "Understanding and Applying Motivation Research" (chapters 3 and 4 of Extension Handbook, 2d ed, edited by Donald J. Blackburn), 1994 (Box 3)
    - "The Impact of Intellectual Leadership" (chapter), undated (Box 3)
  - Classes and curricula
    - Education 601, University of British Columbia, 1977; handout on research in education (Box 3)
    - Program Evaluation (Adult Education 515), University of British Columbia, 1987; syllabus, five student projects; 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Diploma Seminar and Internship in Adult Education (Adult Education 375), University of British Columbia, 1988; program description (Box 3)
    - Theory and Research on Adult Learning (Adult Education 518), University of British Columbia, 1988; syllabus, course development guidelines (Box 3)
    - Evaluation in Adult and Extension Education (Adult Education 579D), Pennsylvania State University, 1989; correspondence, syllabus, course overview (Box 3)
    - Instructional Excellence in Adult and Continuing Education (EDCCV 898.3), University of Saskatchewan, 1993; course outline, reading list (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Adult Education and Community Service in the Community College", undated; more than 30 typescript papers or essays on various aspects of community colleges; most are untitled and it is unclear whether these were intended to be articles, papers, or perhaps merged into a book; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Papers
    - "Access to Education as Related to Economic Development and the Quality of Life", undated (Box 3)
    - Communities, Universities and Change: Recent North American Experience, undated (Box 3)
    - "Political Correctness, Post-Modernism and Academic Adult Education", undated (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - Adult and Continuing Education: Special Study Number 5 of the National Education Finance Project (consultant), 1970 (Box 3)
    - Adult Education Teachers: Accreditation, Certification, Licensing Issues and Options, ca. 1977 (Box 3)
    - An Assessment of Professional Development Education "Needs" of British Columbia's Agricultural Extension Personnel, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Canadian Research in Education: A State of the Art Review (chapter), 1981 (Box 3)
    - Cooperative Program Improvement: An Experiment in ABE In-Service Training, 1971 (Box 3)
    - An Interpretive Review of the 1984 National Adult Education Conference, 1985 (Box 3)
    - National Forums on the Adult Education Delivery System (testimony), 1991 (Box 3)
    - Public Policy in Financing Basic Education for Adults, Volume I: Summary and Recommendations, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Public Policy in Financing Basic Education for Adults, Volume III: Community Case Studies, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Public School Adult Education in Northern Illinois (preface), 1966 (Box 3)
  - Reviews
    - 1966, 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Speeches
    - Agricultural extension in Canada and the United States (outline), undated (Box 3)
    - Adult education and social change, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Literacy in our technological society, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Obligations of leadership, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Extension Supervision" class notes, ca. 1965; Griffith's own notes from a class he took (Box 3)
    - "Our Society's Future" (preface to Cooperative Extension Organization and Administration: Selected Papers), 1967 (Box 3)
      Entire publication is in Reports and studies: Extension education
- Articles (by others)
  - Miscellaneous, collection of photocopies and reprints of articles, book reviews, book chapters, etc from 1855 to 1991 on various adult education topics; also includes two Calvin and Hobbes cartoons; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Conferences
  - Adult Basic Education Conference (Illinois Advisory Council on Adult, Vocational and Technical Education), 1979 (Box 4)
  - Adult Education in Community Colleges (Canadian Association for Adult Education), 1965 (Box 4)
  - Adult Education Research Conference (AERC), 14th Annual, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Adult Education Research Conference (AERC), 31st Annual, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Adult Learning Needs and the Demand for Lifelong Learning (National Institute of Education), 1978 (Box 4)
  - American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE)
    - AAACE 1982 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1983 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1984 Annual (Box 4)
      See also Writings: Reports: An Interpretive Review of the 1984 National Adult Education Conference
    - AAACE 1985 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1987 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1988 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1989 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1990 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1991 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1992 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1993 Annual (Box 4)
    - AAACE 1995 Annual (Box 4)
  - Building Effective Program Linkages (U.S. Department of Education), 1991 (Box 4)
  - Canadian Association for the Study of Adult Education (CASAE), 13th Annual, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Commission of Adult Basic Education (COABE)
    - COABE 1979 Annual (Box 4)
    - COABE 1989 Annual (Box 4)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE)
    - CPAE 1986 Annual (Box 4)
    - CPAE 1989 Annual (Box 4)
    - CPAE 1993 Annual (Box 4)
    - CPAE 1994 Annual (Box 4)
    - CPAE 1998 Annual (Box 4)
  - Future Structures of Post-Secondary Education (Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development), 1973 (Box 4)
  - Economic and Social Perspectives on Adult Illiteracy (Florida Department of Education), 1977 (Box 4)
  - Galaxy Conference on Adult Education, 1969 (Box 4)
  - International Conference of Extension Administrators, 1965 (Box 4)
  - International Intervisitation Program, 4th Annual, 1978 (Box 4)
  - International Symposium on Adult Education, See Correspondence-subject files: International Symposium on Adult Education
  - Interprofessional Continuing Education in the Health Sciences (University of British Columbia), 1992 (Box 4)
  - Invitational Conference on Continuing Education, Manpower Policy, and Lifelong Learning (National Advisory Council on Extension and Continuing Education), 1977 (Box 4)
  - Learning to Build Communities: The Role of Adult Education in Community Development, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Lifelong Learning Research Conference (Department of Agricultural and Extension Education), 1984 (Box 4)
  - Midwest Research-to-Practice Conference, 2d Annual, 1983 (Box 4)
  - National Association for Public and Continuing Education (NAPCAE)
    - NAPCAE 1975 Annual (Box 5)
    - NAPCAE 1976 Annual (Box 5)
    - NAPCAE 1979 Annual (Box 5)